<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Terra australis incognita, or A new southerne discouerie, containing a fifth part of the vvorld. Lately found out by Ferdinand de Quir, a Spanish captaine. Neuer before published. Translated by W.B.</title>
            <title>Relacion de un memorial que ha presentado Pedro Fernandez de Quir. English</title>
            <author>Queirós, Pedro Fernandes de, d. 1615.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1617</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 31 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00688</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10822</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105572</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841299</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841299</idno>
            <idno type="VID">5874</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00688)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5874)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 794:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Terra australis incognita, or A new southerne discouerie, containing a fifth part of the vvorld. Lately found out by Ferdinand de Quir, a Spanish captaine. Neuer before published. Translated by W.B.</title>
                  <title>Relacion de un memorial que ha presentado Pedro Fernandez de Quir. English</title>
                  <author>Queirós, Pedro Fernandes de, d. 1615.</author>
                  <author>W. B., fl. 1613-1617.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 27, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [By B. Norton and J. Bill] for Iohn Hodgetts,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1617.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Relacion de un memorial que ha presentado Pedro Fernandez de Quir.</note>
                  <note>Printers' names from STC.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank except for signature-mark "A" in part of a woodcut.</note>
                  <note>Variant: lacking "Translated by W.B." on title page.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Espíritu Santo Island (Vanuatu) --  Discovery and exploration --  Spanish --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Oceania --  Discovery and exploration --  Spanish --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:5874:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5874:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Terra Australis incognita,</hi> OR A new Southerne DISCOVERIE, CONTAINING A fifth part of the World. <hi>Lately found out</hi> By FERDINAND DE QVIR, a Spaniſh Captaine.</p>
            <p>Neuer before publiſhed.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>LONDON Printed for IOHN HODGETTS. 1617.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="petition">
            <pb facs="tcp:5874:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:5874:2"/>
            <head>THE COPIE OF A Petition preſented to the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> by Captaine <hi>Peter Ferdinand de Quir,</hi> touching the diſcouery of the fift part of the World, called <hi>Terra Australis incognita:</hi> and of the great riches and fertilitie of the ſame.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am called Captaine <hi>Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinand De Quir,</hi> a moſt humble ſeruant and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect of your Maieſties, who in all ſubmiſsion do ſhew vnto you, that this is the eighth Petition, which by mee hath beene preſented to your Maieſties view, to perſwade the conduction of ſome Colonies, vnto the land which your Maieſtie hath commanded to be diſcouered in the Countrey of <hi>Terra Australis incognita.</hi> And yet to this houre no reſolution is taken
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:5874:3"/>in this affaire, neither haue I receiued any an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere or hope, whereby I might reſt aſſured to obtaine my diſpatch, although I haue at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended fourteene moneths in your Court, and haue imployed fourteene yeeres in this Diſcouery, vnto the which I haue beene in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced by the meere goodneſſe of the cauſe, and in the aſſuredneſſe of the ſame haue ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>durated my ſelfe againſt all difficulties and contradictions whatſoeuer. I haue deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately expoſed my ſelfe to a thouſand perils both by ſea and land, I haue diminiſhed and ſuncke my eſtate, I haue beene trauailed with many afflictions in my perſon, and ſuffered ſuch ſtrange and extraordinary croſſes, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they ſeeme almoſt incredible to my ſelfe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and all, that ſo Religious an vndertake ſhould not vnworthily be abandoned. In regard<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> whereof, I doe moſt humbly beſeech your Maieſtie in the bowels of the Diuine Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, that you would be pleaſed to take order that I be not depriued of the fruits of this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne, which with ſuch inſtance I doe deſire and which with ſo much iuſtice are due vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my continuall paines and trauaile: nor that
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:5874:3"/>I be debarred from the effects of ſo conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and well-grounded a requeſt, whoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>incipall ſcope is the glorie of God, and of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>our Maieſtie, and from whence infinite be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits are likely to iſſue forth, which will liue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>long as the fabricke of the world ſhall ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt, and after the diſſolution thereof will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>aine to all Eternitie.</p>
            <p>Touching the extent of theſe Regions <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>wly diſcouered, grounding my iudgment <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> that which I haue ſeene with mine owne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>es, and vpon that which Captaine <hi>Lewes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ez de Torres</hi> Admirall of my Fleet hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented vnto your Maieſtie, The length <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>er of is as great as all <hi>Europe</hi> &amp; <hi>Aſia</hi> the leſſe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>to the Sea of <hi>Bachu, Perſia,</hi> and all the Iles, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ell of the Ocean, as of the <hi>Mediterranean</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, taking <hi>England</hi> &amp; <hi>Iſland</hi> into this account. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> This vnknowne Countrey is the fift part <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Terreſtriall Globe, and extendeth it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>fe to ſuch length, that in probabilitie it is twice greater in Kingdoms and Seignories, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>en all that which at this day doth acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge ſubiection and obedience vnto your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>aieſtie.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:5874:4"/>Theſe Regions know no neighbourhood either of <hi>Turkes</hi> or <hi>Moores,</hi> or of any other Nation which attempteth warre vpon co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning Countreys. The land which we h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> diſcouered is all ſeated within the <hi>To<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> Zone,</hi> and a great tract thereof reacheth vnto the Equinoctiall Circle, which is eleuated <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> them to 90. degrees aboue the Horizon, and in ſome places a little leſſe. And if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſucceſſe prooue anſwerable vnto the hop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> there will be found <hi>Antipodes</hi> vnto the better part of <hi>Africke,</hi> vnto all <hi>Europe,</hi> and to the greater portion of <hi>Aſia.</hi> But you muſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue, that as the Countreys which wee haue diſcouered in 15. degrees of latitude, are bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then <hi>Spaine,</hi> ſo the other which are oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to their eleuation, muſt by proportion and analogie prooue ſome terreſtriall Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe.</p>
            <p>All thoſe quarters ſwarme with an incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible multitude of Inhabitants, wherof ſome are white, others blacke and in colour like vnto thoſe which the <hi>Spaniards</hi> call <hi>Mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> or halfe-<hi>Moores,</hi> &amp; others of a mingled com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion. Some weare their haire long, black,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:5874:4"/>and ſcattered, others haue their haire criſped and thicke, &amp; others very yellow and bright. Which diuerſitie is an apparant argument, that there is commerce and communication amongſt them. And this conſideration toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the bounty which Nature hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed on the ſoile, their inexperience of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tillerie and Guns, and their vnskilfulneſſe in labouring in Mines, with other ſemblable circumſtances, doth induce mee to inferre, that all the Countrey is rich &amp; well-peopled. It ſeemeth they know little what belongeth to artificiall trades; for they haue neither for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifications nor walles, and liue without the awe of Kings or lawes. They are a ſimple people cantoned into ſeuerall ſexts, and facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, &amp; exerciſe much diſagreement amongſt themſelues. The Armes which they vſe are bowes and arrowes, which are not poiſoned or ſteeped in the iuice of venemous hearbes, as the cuſtome is of many other Countreys; They do alſo carrie clubs, truncheons, pikes, darts to hurle with the arme, all which are framed only of wood. They doe couer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the waſte or girdling-place downe
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:5874:5"/>to the halfe of their thighes, they are very ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious of cleanlines, tractable, gleeful, &amp; won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derouſly addicted to be gratefull vnto thoſe that doe them a courteſie, as I haue experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced many times. The which doth build in me a beliefe, that with the aſsiſtance of God, if they may be gently and amiably intreated, they will bee found very docible and eaſie of manage, and that wee ſhall without much worke accommodate our ſelues vnto them. And it is moſt neceſſary to obſerue this way of ſweetnes, eſpecially in the beginning, that the inhabitants may be drawne along to this ſo holy and ſauing an end, whereof we ought to take a particular care and zeale, aſwell in ſmall things, as in matters of more impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. Their houſes are built of wood, coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and tiled with Palme-tree leaues, they haue pitchers and veſſels made of earth, they are not without the myſterie of weauing, and other curioſities of that kind. They worke on Marble, they haue Flutes, Drummes, and wooden ſpoones, they ſet apart certaine pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces for Oratories &amp; prayers, and for Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yards. Their Gardens are artificially ſeuered
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:5874:5"/>into beds, bordered and faſhioned with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct limits; Mother of Pearle and the ſhels which containe Pearle, they haue in much vſe and eſtimation, of which they make wedges, raſors, ſawes, culters, and ſuch like inſtruments; They alſo doe make thereof Pearles and great beads to weare about their neckes. They that doe dwell in the Ilands, haue boates very artificially made, and excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly commodious for ſailing, which is a certaine argument that they confine vpon other Nations that are of a more poliſhed and elegant behauiour. And this alſo they haue of our husbandry, that they cut Cockes and gelde Boares.</p>
            <p>Their bread is vſually made of three ſorts of rootes, which grow there in great abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance. Neither doe they imploy much la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour in making this bread, for they doe one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly roſte the rootes vntill they are ſoft and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. They are very pleſant to the taſte, whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome and nouriſhing, they are of a good length, there being of them of an Ell long, and the halfe of that in bigneſſe.</p>
            <p>There is great ſtore of excellent fruits in
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:5874:6"/>theſe Countreys. There are ſixe kindes of Maple trees, Almond trees of foure ſorts, and other trees called Obi, reſembling almoſt in fruit and greatneſſe our Quince trees. Innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable Wallnut trees are found there, and of Citron trees the Barbarians haue no dearth, nor of other great and excellent fruits, which we haue ſeene and taſted. They haue more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer Sugar-Canes, large in ſize and in great plenty, they haue knowlegde of our ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie Apples; they haue Palme-trees without number, out of which there may eaſily bee drawne a iuice, which will make a liquor al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luding much to wine, as alſo whey, vineger, and hony, the kernels thereof are exceeding ſweet. And they haue fruits which the <hi>Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> call <hi>Cocos,</hi> which being greene doe make a kind of twine, and the pith is almoſt like in taſte vnto the creame of milke: When they are ripe they ſerue for meat and drinke both by land and ſea. And when they wither and fall from the tree, there ſweateth out an oyle from them, which is very good to burne in lampes, and is medicinable for wounds, and not vnpleaſant tobe eaten. Of their rindes
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:5874:6"/>or barkes there are made bottles, and other like veſſels, and the inner skin doth ſerue for tow or moſſe to ſtop and cloſe vp the leakes in ſhippes. Men doe make Cables and other cordage of them, which are of ſufficient ſtrength to draw a Canon, and are fit for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther domeſticke vſes. But that which is more ſpeciall, they do there vſe the leaues of Palme trees, which they amaſſe together, to make ſailes of them for veſſels of ſmall bulke and burthen. They make likewiſe fine thinne mattes of them, and they doe ſerue for tiles to couer the houſe without, and for hangings to cloath the houſe within. And theſe hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes are built of the branches of trees that are ſtreight and long, of which they doe like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe make pikes, and other ſorts of weapons, as alſo oares to row with, and vtenſils for the houſe. You are to note, that theſe Palme-trees reſemble Vines, from whence they gather their materials for Wine all the yeere long, which they make without much coſt, or la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour. Amongſt their herbage and garden fruits; Wee haue ſeene Melons, Peares great and little, and ſundry ſorts of pot-hearbes.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:5874:7"/>And they haue alſo beanes. For fleſh, they are ſtored with a great number of Hogges which are like vnto ours, they haue Hennes, Capons, Partriges, Duckes, Turtles, Pigeons, Stocke-doues, and Goats, as one of my Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines doth relate. And the <hi>Indians</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues haue aſſured vs that there are Cowes and Oxen. There are alſo ſundry ſorts of fiſh, Harghi, Perſereyes, Lize, Soles, Troutes, Shads, Macabiſes, Caſanes, Pampani, Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chards, Thorne-backs or Skate-fiſh, Cuculi, Congers, Porpoſes, Rochets, Muskles, Lob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and many other, the names whereof I cannot now remember. But it is probable that there are diuers other kinds, ſince thoſe which I haue recounted were taken hard by our ſhips. And vpon ripe and ſerious conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of that which I haue repreſented vnto you, a man may eaſily collect, that ſuch plentifull and different varieties of all things, may yeeld large meanes to inhabite there, with great and ſingular delights. There is ſtuffe for Marchpanes and ſweet confections of all ſorts, without borrowing any ſpice for the compoſition of them elſwhere. And for
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:5874:7"/>my Mates the Marriners, beſides thoſe parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars which I haue before ſet downe, there will be no want of Gammons, Sauſages, and other ſalt meats which hogges doe yeeld; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of vineger, ſpiceries, and other ſauces that ſerue for delicacy, and to awake the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite. And you muſt obſerue, that many of theſe things, are the ſame with thoſe which wee haue in our parts, and poſſibly they are there in greater abundance; by all which it is eaſily to be coniectured, that this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey is fit for the production of all that which groweth in <hi>Europe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The riches which I haue ſeene in thoſe parts, is Siluer and Pearle; another Captaine in his Relation, doth report that he hath ſeen Gold, which are the three moſt precious dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings that lie and are cheriſhed in the boſome of Nature. Wee haue alſo both of vs ſeene many Nutmegs, much Maſticke, Ginger, and Pepper. There is alſo Cinnamum; and it is likely that Cloues may bee found in thoſe parts, ſince ſo many other ſorts of Spiceries and aromaticall drugges doe proſper there; and that the rather, becauſe theſe Countryes
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:5874:8"/>lie very neere the parallell of the Iles of <hi>Terr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natte, Bachian,</hi> and the <hi>Moluccos.</hi> There an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> likewiſe materials for all ſorts of ſilke, and we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> haue ſeene Aniſe-ſeed, and excellent good Ebony, as alſo other kinds of wood proper for the building of as many ſhippes as one will deſire, and ſtuffe to make ſailesf or the ſame. Three ſorts of materials there are wherewithall to make cordage, and one o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> them is very like vnto our hempe. More o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer out of the oyle of <hi>Cocos,</hi> whereof I haue already made mention, there is a kind of bi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuminous ſtuffe extracted, called <hi>Galagald</hi> which may bee well vſed for pitch. They make alſo a kinde of roſen with which the <hi>Indians</hi> pitch their boats, which they call <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raques.</hi> And ſince there are Goates and Cowes in thoſe parts, without queſtion we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhall haue Goat-skins, leather, tallow, and fleſh in full abundance. The Bees which we haue ſeene there doe make proofe, that there will be no ſcarcety of hony and waxe. And there is good appearance to diſcouer many other things which are not yet known, to ſay nothing touching thefor me and ſite of the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:5874:8"/>Countrey. Vnto all which if that be adioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, which the induſtry of man may contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to thoſe parts, ſince there is ſuch aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of commodities which the Countrey it ſelfe doth yeeld, and ſuch hope to tranſport thither thoſe things which grow with vs, the beſt and choiſeſt whereof that <hi>Peru</hi> and new <hi>Spaine</hi> bring foorth, I haue reſolued to tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre thither; it is to be hoped, that this will ſo enrich that Countrey, that it will be able to nouriſh and furniſh not only the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of the ſame, and thoſe of <hi>America,</hi> but giue an acceſſion vnto <hi>Spaine</hi> it ſelfe both of riches and extent of Command: and this may be accompliſhed after the maner which I haue proiected, and will vnfold vnto thoſe which ſhall lend an aſsiſting hand for the guiding and conſummation of this worke.</p>
            <p>Now by that land which we haue already diſcouered outwardly and along the ſhores, without entrance into the inward parts, we doe conceiue a certaine argument, that as much riches, commodities, and greatneſſe, may be hoped for from thence, as we haue already in theſe Countreyes. And you may
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:5874:9"/>be pleaſed to vnderſtand, that my principall ayme was to take a view only of theſe ample regions which wee haue diſcouered: for by reaſon of many ſickeneſſes which haue wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened me, and ſome other chances whereof I will at this time make no mention, I was not able to ſuruay all which I deſired, neither could I in a full moneth haue ſeene all that, which I was of my ſelfe inclinable to view.</p>
            <p>You are not to make your iudgement of the <hi>Indians</hi> that inhabit theſe Countreys, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the honour of the people here, or conceiue them to be affected with the ſame deſires, pleaſures, neceſsities, or eſtimation of things that we are: But you are to make ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count that they are a people whoſe care is ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diouſly placed vpon this, that they may liue eaſily in this world, and paſſe their dayes with the leaſt paine and perturbation they can. And this is indeed their practiſe, for they doe not beſtow themſelues on thoſe things, which with ſuch vexation and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment we here labour to obtaine.</p>
            <p>There are found in this Countrey as many comodities, both for the ſupport &amp; delecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:5874:9"/>of the life of man, as may be expected from a ſoile that is manureable, pleaſant and very temperate. It is a fat and a fertile land, wherein many places Clay is found, which will prooue of excellent vſe to build houſes, and to make tiles and brickes, and will ſerue for Whatſoeuer is vſually made of earth. There is no dearth of Marble and other good ſtones, wherewith if there be occaſion there may be built ſtructures of greater State and Magnificence.</p>
            <p>The Countrey aboundeth in wood, fit for all workes and vſes, whereunto the ſame is commonly put. There are ſpatious &amp; good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly plaines, and fields that are diuided and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terlaced with brookes, trenches, and riuers. There are great and high rockes, ſundry tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, riuers great and little, on which water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milles for corne may with much commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe be built and placed, as alſo Engins to make Sugar, Tucking-milles, Forges, and all other inſtruments which in their vſe doe require water.</p>
            <p>We haue found Salt-pits there, and which is a note of the fertilitie of the ſoile, there are
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:5874:10"/>in many places Canes whereof ſome are fiue or ſixe handfuls thicke, with fruit anſwera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to that proportion. The top of that fruit is very ſmall and hard, and the skin thereof is exceeding ſweet. There are alſo Flints for fire, equall in goodneſſe with thoſe of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drid.</hi> The bay of Saint <hi>Iames</hi> and Saint <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip</hi> hath twenty leagues of banke, and is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out mudde; Into which there is a ſure and ſafe entrance both by day and night. It is ſheltered and couered with many houſes, which in the day time we haue ſeene a farre off to ſend foorth ſmoake, and in the night to ſhew foorth fire.</p>
            <p>The Hauen called <hi>The true Croſſe</hi> is of that ſpacious capacitie, that it is able to containe a thouſand Shippes. The botome as I haue ſaid is without mudde, and hath a blackiſh coloured ſand wherewithall it is couered. There are no gulfes or deepe pits, but an aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured and eaſie anchorage in what part ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer you will, from forty to halfe a fadome; and it is betweene the mouthes of two ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, the one whereof is as great as that of <hi>Quadalguiuer,</hi> &amp; hath mud of a fadom deepe,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:5874:10"/>ouer which our Shaloppes and boates did paſſe.</p>
            <p>For the other riuer, when our Skiffs went to water there, they found the entrance ſafe and eaſie. And a man may from the very mouth of the riuer take in as much freſh wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter as he will. The place where ſhips may be vnloaded hath three leagues of grauell, min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled with little flints blackiſh and very hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie, which will ſerue for balaſte for ſhippes. The banke is ſtraight and vnited, on which much greene graſſe doth grow and proſper, and that makes me to conceiue that the Sea doth not beat or rage thereupon; I obſerue that the trees are ſtreight, and the branches not diſmembred, which is a token that there are no tempeſts there. Touching the Port, beſides the commodities which I haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready diſcourſed of, there is one of maruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous pleaſure and contentation. And that is, that at the dawning of the day you ſhal heare from a wood which is neere at hand, a ſweet and various harmony of a thouſand birdes of all ſorts, among which we could diſtinguiſh the Nightingales, Black-birds, Quailes, Gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finches,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:5874:11"/>Swallowes almoſt without num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, Parrochitos, and one Parret we marked there, and creatures of ſundrie other kinds, euen downe to Graſſe-hoppers, and Field<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crickets.</p>
            <p>Euerie Morning and Euening wee recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued a moſt odoriferous ſweet ſmell, ſent vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our noſtrells from the infinite diuerſitie of Flowers and Hearbes which grow there, amongſt which we obſerued the bloſſomes of Oranges and Baſil. All which (with a number of other varieties) doth make vs thinke that the ayre is cleare and healthie, and that the nature of the place is of a good tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perature. The Hauen &amp; the Bay are therfore of the greater eſtimation, becauſe they haue the neighbourhood of ſo many goodly I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands that are there, and eſpecially of thoſe ſeuen, which are ſaid to haue two hundreth leagues of extent: and ſurely one of them (which is ſome twelue leagues diſtant from the Hauen) is fiftie leagues in circuit. In briefe SIR, I doe affirme vnto your Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, that you may giue commaund to haue a goodly and great Citie built in this Port and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:5874:11"/>Bay, which are in fifteene degrees and fortie minutes of the Southerne Eleuation, and thoſe that ſhall inhabite there, ſhall haue plentie of riches, and all other conueniencies which they can deſire. Time will ſhew and diſcouer all theſe commodities, and in this place there may be made the diſcharge and vnloading of all the wares and merchandi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zes of the Countries of <hi>Chilly, Peru, Panania, Macaraqua, Guttimala, New-Spaine, Terre-natte,</hi> and the <hi>Philippines,</hi> all which Countries are vnder the commaund of your Maieſtie. And if you ſhall acquire vnto your ſelfe the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion of theſe Seigniories which I do now preſent, I doe make ſo great an eſteeme of them, that beſides their being the Key of all the reſt, they will (in my opinion) prooue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother <hi>China</hi> or <hi>Iapan,</hi> and equallize the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther rich Ilands which are on this ſide of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia,</hi> in trafique of curious and pretious mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandizes, to ſpeake nothing of the augmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation and extent of your power, and the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhment which you may make vnto your ſelfe of your Dominions, by the acceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſo great a Countrie. That which I
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:5874:12"/>haue giuen vnto your viewe in my diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, is of much ſlenderneſſe, in regard of that which I doe probably conceiue of this land, the which I am readie to make appeare in the preſence of Mathematicians. Neither will I vexe this paper to demonſtrate vnto you, that theſe Countries will be able at the firſt aboord to nouriſh twentie thouſand Spaniards. In ſumme, this is SIR, the world whereof Spaine is the Center, and that which I haue related, is the nayle by which you may iudge of the whole bodie, which I pray you to take into your obſeruation.</p>
            <p>You may iudge by that which I haue alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die repreſented, what the goodneſſe and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perature of the ayre is: whereunto this may be added for a further teſtimonie, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though all our Companie were ſtrangers, yet neuer a one of them was ſicke, albeit they were in continuall trauell and labour, and did ſometimes ſweat, and ſometimes take wet. They dranke water faſting, and fed manie times on that which the earth did there bring forth. Neither had they any regard to keepe themſelues from the Serenes, nor from
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:5874:12"/>the Moone or Sunne, which indeed in thoſe parts is not ouer-vehement. Onely about Mid-night, they couered themſelues with Wooll, and did lye and repoſe themſelues thereupon. And for the Inhabitants, they are commonly healthie, and many of them verie aged, although they haue nothing but the bare earth for their pallet: which is an argument of the wholeſomeneſſe and pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the ſoyle. For if it were a wet and weeping ground, or had any viciouſneſſe in the mould, they would raiſe their lodgings higher from the earth, as they doe that liue in the <hi>Philippines,</hi> and other Countries which I haue viewed. And this is further confirmed by their Fleſh and Fiſh, which although it bee vnſalted, yet will it keepe ſweete, and without corruption two daies. And the fruits which are brought from thence are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding good, as wee had proofe by two that I tooke care to bring along with mee, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they had not their full maturitie and grouth when I gathered them from the Tree. Wee haue not ſeene any barren and ſandie ground, nor any Thiſtles, or trees that
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:5874:13"/>are thornie or whoſe rootes doe ſhew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, no Mariſhes or Fennes, no Snow vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Mountaines, no Snakes or Serpents, no Crocodiles in the Riuers, no Wormes that vſe with vs to hurt and conſume our Grayne, and to worke vs ſo much diſpleaſure in our houſes, no Fleas, Cater-pillers, or Gnats. This is a Prerogatiue that hath the aduauntage of all the priuiledges that nature hath beſtowed on other places, and is worthie to be compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, or rather preferred before any delicacie of the Countries of India, ſome of which are abandoned and vnhabited, meerely by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of theſe incommodities, and of ſundrie others that are diſtaſtfull vnto the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants, as my ſelfe haue oftentimes beene wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <p>Theſe (SIR) are the vertues and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies of the Countries which I haue diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered, of which I haue already taken the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion in the name of your Maieſtie, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der your Royall-Banner, as appeareth by the Acts which I keepe ſafely in my power, whereunto I proceeded after this enſuing manner.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:5874:13"/>Firſt (SIR) wee erected a Croſſe, and built a Church in honour of our Ladie of <hi>Loretto.</hi> Then wee cauſed twentie Maſſes to be celebrated there, and our troupes made haſt thither to gaine ſome Indulgences. We alſo made a ſolemne Proceſſion, and obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the Feaſt of the bleſſed Sacrament, the which was carried in Proceſſion, your Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner being euer diſplayed, and marching be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it, through a great Circuit of Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, which were honoured with the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the ſame.</p>
            <p>In three ſeuerall places wee ſet vp your Titles, in euerie one of which wee prepared and erected two Columnes, with the Armes of your Maieſtie tricked and garniſhed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon: ſo that I may with good right affirme, that ſince this will challenge to be one of the Parts of the World, the Impreſſe of <hi>Plus vl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra</hi> is accompliſhed, and becauſe it ſtretcheth vnto the continent, whether it be forward or behind it skills not, the bounds of your Dominions are with much ſpaciouſneſſe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged. Now all this which I haue perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, receiueth its root from this the faithfull
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:5874:14"/>zeale which I beare vnto your Maieſtie, that to all the Titles which you alreadie doe poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe, you may adjoyne this which I repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and that the name of TERRA AV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STRALIS INCOGNITA may be bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zoned and ſpread ouer the face of the whole world to the glorie of God, who hath reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led this Countrie, and hath giuen mee the grace to guide my courſe thither, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to the preſence of your Maieſtie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whom I do preſent &amp; proſtrate my ſelfe with the ſame affection and zeale vnto this worke which I had before, and which hath growne vp with mee as it were from my cradle, and for the nobleneſſe and worth thereof, I doe ſtill tender and cheriſh the ſame with the greateſt loue that can be.</p>
            <p>I doe confidently beleeue, that your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie doth vſe ſo much prudence in your Councels, and are ſo magnanimous and full of Chriſtian pietie, that you will (with your beſt care) embrace all the conducements which may further the habitation of theſe new-diſcouered Countries. And the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall reaſon to put a tye and obligation vpon
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:5874:14"/>vs not to leaue them abandoned, is, in regard that this is the ſole ordinarie way to eſtabliſh the knowledge of God, and faith amongſt them, and to bring to paſſe that his name may be adored and called vpon, where the Deuill vſurpeth ſo much reuerence and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocation. And this ought to bee embraced with the more readineſſe, becauſe it is the channell to conuay and diſperſe all aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of commodities amongſt your ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects. And hereby you ſhall be eaſed of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny diſturbances and vexations, which will aſſuredly be put vpon you, in caſe the Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickes ſhould enter &amp; neſtle there, and ſhould vent their erronious doctrines amongſt them, whereby they would conuert all the bleſſings which I haue hitherto recounted vnto you, into aſſured incommodities and miſchiefes, and would arrogate vnto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues the name of the Lords of the <hi>Indias,</hi> to the vtter ruine and deſolation of thoſe coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries. I make no queſtion but your Maieſty well weigheth of what importance this dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of which I ſpeak may proue, &amp; what euil conſequence ſome other hazards may carrie
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:5874:15"/>with them, which are either at this time im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent, or may ſucceed hereafter. And if this ſhould happen, it would coſt you innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable thouſands of gold and men, before you ſhall be able to giue a remedie vnto the ſame. Acquire therefore SIR, whiles that occaſion is offered you (that one day you may pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe heauen vnto your ſelfe;) acquire (I ſay) with a little mony which you miſ-place vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Peru,</hi> a neuer-dying reputation, and this <hi>New-world</hi> with all the benefits which it rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth out vnto you. And ſince there is none that craueth a reward for this good tidings that is brought you concerning ſo great and ſingular a bleſſing, which God hath bin plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to lock vp vntil your happie time, I am he SIR, that doe demaund it, and my humble requeſt vnto you is only this, that you would be of that gratiouſneſſe vnto mee, as to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch and giue me mine anſwer: for the Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions are readie to hoyſe ſayle, and I haue much way to goe, and many things muſt be fitted and diſpoſed for the voyage. There is no houre paſſes, which carryeth not with it an aſſured loſſe both in regard of ſpirituall
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:5874:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>and temporal bleſſings, the dammage wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of can neuer be made vp, or repaired.</p>
            <p>If vpon a bare ſuſpition <hi>Chriſtoferus Colum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus</hi> did purſue his deſigne with ſo much ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinacie, you are not to account it ſtrange in me, if the things which I haue beheld with mine eyes, and touched with mine hands, doe put ſome kind of conſtraint vpon me to be importunate.</p>
            <p>Let it therefore pleaſe your Maieſtie, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt ſo many expedients which you haue at hand, to ſeuer and put apart ſome one for the accompliſhment of this worke, that after all theſe languiſhments, I may at length meet with the ſucceſſe of my deſires. I doe aſſure you that you will find my propoſitions moſt iuſt, and that I ſhall be of ſufficiencie to giue you ſatisfaction in all things. This, SIR, is a great worke, againſt which the deuill doth bandy himſelfe with all the puiſſance hee may; And it is not conſonant to reaſon, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandon theſe Countreys to his tyranny and power, which doe know your Maieſtie for their Patron and Defender.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
